ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
28 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的28年後）
THE GRANZ CHANNEL IN THE CENTRAL LANDS
（中央諸國，葛蘭茲海峽）
This place has always been
這裡一直以來
a dangerous area to navigate by ship.
都是船隻航行的危險地帶
So all sorts of things wash up here.
總有各式各樣的東西漂流過來
Everyone in the village used to
至今為止，都是靠村裡的大家
get together to clean it up but…
一起清理，不過…
You ran out of people and this was left alone?
你們已經人手不足 所以只好丟著不管？
Before, it used to be a beautiful beach
這裡以前可是如寶石般璀璨的海岸
with transparent water.
海水晶瑩剔透
I know.
我知道
Will this do as a reward?
如果用這個當作報酬可以嗎？
The Great Mage Flamme's book, huh?
大魔法使弗蘭梅的著作嗎？
Mistress Frieren…
芙莉蓮大人…
Is this the only grimoire in this village?
村裡就只有這本魔導書嗎？
Yes.
是的
Okay.
我知道了
I'll accept your cleanup request.
我們會接受你們清掃的委託
That grimoire is fake, right?
那本魔導書是贗品吧？
You've been studying like I told you to.
看來妳有聽話好好讀書呢
Good job, Fern.
值得稱讚，費倫
Books by Flamme are all fake.
所謂弗蘭梅的著作沒有真品
This is another poorly made fake.
這個也不過又是一本粗製濫造的假貨
Why did you accept it then?
那您為什麼要接受委託呢？
There are people in need of help.
看起來他們很需要幫忙
I don't think it's just out of kindness.
我不覺得您是純粹出於善意接受的
You're right, this is for myself.
說得沒錯，我是為了我自己才接受的
Seems like we're going to be here for a while.
看來又要在這裡待上一陣子了
As always, thank you, Fern.
一直以來謝謝妳了，費倫
I added one extra on the house.
我多送了一個
Thank you.
謝謝您
It's been three months already.
已經三個月了
-Have you gotten used to the village? -Yes.
-習慣村裡的生活了嗎？ -是
The coast is very chilly this time of year,
每年這個時節的海邊都很冷
so be careful.
要注意喔
It's winter already.
已經入冬了
She's still sleeping.
她還在睡
This place is a mess.
房間裡到處亂七八糟的
I just cleaned it up yesterday.
明明昨天我才打掃過
Mistress Frieren, it's morning. Please wake up.
芙莉蓮大人，已經早上了，該起床了
Let's go clean the coast.
該去清理海岸了
It's freezing.
好冷喔
I was thinking…
我突然覺得…
What?
什麼？
Mistress Frieren, are you perhaps
芙莉蓮大人，或許您…
a very slobbish person?
是個很邋遢的人？
Every morning, I wake you up,
每天早上都是我叫您起床
feed you, and clothe you.
餵飯、更衣
I'm basically your mother.
這樣我根本是您的媽媽了
I can do it on my own.
我也可以自己來
But then you would be sleeping until the afternoon.
那您會一路睡到下午吧
Yeah.
對啊
Well, whatever. I've given up already.
算了，無所謂啦，我已經放棄了
Sorry.
對不起
How were you traveling as the party of heroes?
請問您跟勇者一行人 旅行時是什麼樣子呢？
There was nobody to take care of you, right?
應該沒有人照顧您吧？
I always overslept.
我總是睡過頭
They didn't get mad at you?
沒人對您發火過嗎？
They did, just once.
有啊，就一次
Just once?
就一次？
They must've been very kind.
勇者們還真是心胸寬大
They were very tolerant.
他們很有肚量的
Once in a while, Heiter would click his tongue though.
還有就是海塔偶爾會咂嘴這樣
Sorry.
對不起
-Hey… -I don't blame you though.
-喂… -我懂你的心情
I think they were pretty mad.
那個一般來說就是很火大了
How is the cleaning going?
清掃得還算順利嗎？
There's about one-third of it left.
還剩三分之一就完成了
Will you make it in time for the New Year's celebration?
能夠趕在新年祭之前結束嗎？
Just barely.
差不多
Well then, I really hope
我真心希望
you are able to watch the sunrise this time,
這次您能來看看這裡的日出
Mistress Frieren.
芙莉蓮大人
What's the connection between
請問清理海岸跟新年祭之間
cleaning the coast and New Year's?
有什麼關聯呢？
In this village, they have a custom
這個村子在新年祭
of watching the sunrise on New Year's Day.
有看日出的風俗
The sunlight reflects off of the transparent ocean
據說陽光會在晶透的海面上反射
and it's very pretty, apparently.
很是美不勝收喔
You didn't see it, Mistress Frieren?
芙莉蓮大人，您沒看過嗎？
Do you think I'd be able to wake up?
妳覺得我爬得起來嗎？
I guess not.
說起來也是
Let's hurry. We don't have much time.
加快動作吧，時間不多了
The water quality is good too.
水質也很清澈
We somehow finished a day before.
總算在新年祭前一天完成了
It looks nothing like before.
看起來簡直判若兩地
You're a life saver, Mistress Frieren.
真是幫了大忙了，芙莉蓮大人
You will participate in the New Year's celebration, right?
兩位會參加新年祭吧？
Yeah.
嗯
We look forward to seeing you there.
我們很歡迎兩位參加
Have you gone insane, Mistress Frieren?
您是認真的嗎，芙莉蓮大人？
You have to wake up before the sun rises.
要參加的話 得在太陽升起前就起床喔
It's impossible.
那我做不到
I'll stay up all night, so it's fine.
我會徹夜不睡的，所以沒問題
You want to watch the sunrise that much?
不惜通宵不睡也要看到日出嗎？
Honestly, it doesn't interest me at all.
說實話，我對看日出沒有興趣
But that's why I have to check it out.
但正因如此，我要去確認一下
I don't really understand.
您說的理由我真的不懂
Yeah…
說得也是
Why didn't you come to the New Year's celebration?
妳怎麼沒有來參加新年祭？
Heiter is so disappointed, he can't get out of bed.
海塔都失望到起不了床了
Poor thing.
真可憐
He's just out of commission because he drank too much.
他只是喝太多喝到罷工而已
All of you made it, so who cares?
你們都去了不就好了嗎？
We wanted
我們希望
you to enjoy it too.
妳也能玩得開心
It's just a sunrise.
只是日出而已
There's nothing to enjoy.
有什麼好玩的？
No, you'd enjoy it.
當然有了
Why?
為什麼這麼說？
Because that's the kind of person you are.
因為妳就是那種人啊
She's sleeping…
還在睡…
She's sleeping! Wake up, Mistress Frieren!
她還在睡！快起床，芙莉蓮大人！
You'll miss the New Year's celebration!
這樣會錯過新年祭的！
-Mom… -I'm not your mother!
-媽… -誰是媽媽啊！
Why do I have to do this?
為什麼連這種事情都要我做呢？
Thank you, Fern.
謝謝妳，費倫
It's pretty, that's for sure.
確實是很漂亮啦
But it's not worth waking up so early.
不過也沒有到值得早起來看的地步啊
Himmel doesn't know me at all.
欣梅爾根本就不懂我嘛
Fern, I'll go back to sleep…
費倫，回去睡回籠覺…
Mistress Frieren, it's so beautiful.
芙莉蓮大人，真的很美呢
You think so?
是這樣嗎？
It's just a sunrise.
只是平凡的日出啊
But you look like you're having fun, Mistress Frieren.
但您看起來很開心呢，芙莉蓮大人
Well, that's because you were smiling…
那是因為剛剛妳笑了…
I couldn't have
如果是我自己一個人
seen this sunrise on my own.
肯定就看不到這個日出了
Of course.
那是當然的
You can't wake up on your own, after all.
畢竟您沒辦法靠自己起床
This is your family?
他們是你的家人嗎？
It was a long time ago.
已經是很久以前的事了
My village was attacked by demons.
我的村莊遭到魔族襲擊
What are you doing?
你在做什麼？
I'm praying.
我在祈禱
People go back to nothing when they die.
人死後就回歸虛無了
They go to heaven.
是去了天國才對
Until a few thousand years ago, most people
直到數千年前，大部分的人
believed that you go back to nothing.
都是相信死後會回歸虛無
And dwarves value tradition.
而矮人族很看重傳統
But I'm skeptical about heaven too.
不過我其實 也很懷疑天國的存在就是了
With the current level of magic,
以目前的魔法水準
we can't observe souls after they die.
無法觀察到人死後的靈魂
So we can't prove its existence.
所以也無法證實天國的存在
I don't really care, either way.
不管存不存在，我都無所謂就是了
I agree.
是這樣沒錯
I don't care whether it exists or not.
不管天國是否存在，我也都沒關係
Is a priest allowed to say that? Are you a corrupt priest?
你可以說這種話嗎，酒肉僧侶？
But even if it doesn't exist,
但是就算天國不存在
I believe it should.
我也認為它應該要存在
Why?
為什麼呢？
Because it's more convenient that way.
因為存在的話就方便多了
If people try so desperately to live only to become
如果人們一輩子拚命地活下來
nothing in the end, that's just not right.
最終卻回歸虛無，我認為是不對的
I'd rather believe that
我寧可相信
they are living lavish lives in heaven.
他們在天國過著奢華的享樂生活
I like that better.
這樣更好，不是嗎？
It's definitely more convenient.
那確實是很方便呢
I guess I'll pray.
我也來祈禱吧
Yeah.
嗯
28 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO THE BREDT REGION IN THE CENTRAL LANDS
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的28年後 中央諸國，布雷特地區）
Eisen, I came to visit.
艾冉，我來看你了
That's how you greet someone you see for the first time in 30 years?
妳跟三十年不見的人打招呼 就只是這樣而已嗎？
It's only been 30 years.
只不過三十年而已
I guess so.
說得也是
I can't believe you took in an apprentice.
真沒想到妳竟然會收徒弟
Eisen, is there anything
艾冉，你有什麼
you need help with?
需要幫忙的地方嗎？
Frieren, I heard you asked
芙莉蓮，我聽說妳
the same thing to Heiter.
問了海塔一樣的問題
It's still not my time.
給我送終的話未免太早了
How did you know?
你是怎麼知道的？
Because we wrote to each other.
因為我們一直有書信往來啊
You're quite loyal despite your looks.
沒想到你外表粗曠，卻這麼重禮儀
You're too cold, that's all.
是妳太過冷漠了吧
And so, is there anything you need help with?
所以，你有什麼需要幫忙的地方嗎？
Voll Basin, huh? Brings back memories.
佛爾盆地嗎？真是令人懷念
-You've been here before? -Yeah, a long time ago.
-妳來過這裡嗎？ -很久以前的事了
She said "a long time ago."
她說“很久以前”
How long ago is that?
那會是多久以前啊？
Primitive times?
是原始時代嗎？
I'm not that old.
我可沒辦法活那麼久喔
So, what are you looking for?
所以你要找的東西是什麼？
Great Flamme Mage's Notes.
大魔法使弗蘭梅的手記
All right…
可以是可以啦…
Most of Flamme's books are fake.
但大部分弗蘭梅的著作都是贗品
I have a clue.
我有線索
Heiter compiled Flamme's records
海塔總結了聖都裡
that were preserved in the Holy City
關於弗蘭梅所有紀錄
and discovered this location.
然後推理找出這個位置
Her real notes are somewhere in the Voll Basin.
她真正的手記就在佛爾盆地某個地方
Frieren, you should know.
芙莉蓮，這件事妳應該也知情
That corrupt priest…
那個酒肉僧侶…
He researched that much?
竟然查到這個地步了？
Fine. Let's find a large tree first.
知道了，先從大棵的樹找起
A large tree?
大棵的樹？
That'll be endless. There are so many.
那樣要找到何時？ 那樣的樹多到數不清
Well, I guess you have lots of time.
不過我想妳時間也很多就是了
Yeah.
是啊
But Fern will get mad, so let's get it done quickly.
但費倫會不高興的 所以趕緊找一找吧
Let's search as efficiently as possible.
請盡可能用有效率的方式找吧
You've changed.
妳變了呢
You never used to
妳以前
care about other people's time.
從來不在乎別人的時間
Well, Fern is scary when she gets mad.
因為費倫生氣起來很可怕嘛
I see. I'll watch out then.
這樣啊，那我也會注意的
Mistress Frieren,
芙莉蓮大人
there was a large tree
西邊有一棵
engulfing some ruins in the west.
圍著遺跡生長的大樹
This way.
在這個方向
Okay.
知道了
Hey, why did you decide to search for Flamme's Notes?
我說啊 你為什麼想要找弗蘭梅的手記？
I felt pity.
我覺得太可憐了
I felt pity
我覺得妳跟欣梅爾
for you and Himmel.
實在太可憐了
On that day, 30 years ago,
三十年前的那天
you said that you wished you knew more about Himmel.
妳說過 要是能再多了解欣梅爾一點就好了
Those words are something
那些話
you should tell him directly.
妳應該直接告訴他本人
They say that Great Flamme Mage's Notes
據說大魔法使弗蘭梅的手記
include records of
記載了
her communicating with the dead.
她跟死者的對話
That's just a fairy tale.
聽起來就跟童話故事一樣呢
Plus, it's not like I want to see him again.
況且事到如今 我也沒想要再見他一面
Every magic spell
所有的魔法
started out as a fairy tale.
最初都像童話故事一樣
Plus, you want to get to know Himmel, right?
而且妳想要了解欣梅爾，對吧？
That's why I talked to Heiter.
所以我才去找海塔商量這件事
I knew you were probably feeling regret,
想必妳一定也感到很後悔
so I wanted to help you out.
所以我想幫妳一把
Mistress Frieren, the tree and the ruins
芙莉蓮大人，大樹跟遺跡
are protected by a strong barrier.
都有強大的結界保護著
Since 1,000 years ago,
就算過了千年之久
I've been in the palm of her hand.
我依舊如師父所預料的那樣
What an unreliable guard.
真是不可靠的守衛
Not really.
也不全然是那樣啦
Once this matures,
只要它長大了
it will protect this place even after 1,000 years.
就一定會守護這個地方 甚至可長達千年之久
You'll be dead by then.
到時候師父已經死了吧
But not you.
但妳還不會死
One day, you will make a big mistake
有朝一日 妳會因為鑄下大錯而悔恨不已
and desire to know more about humans.
並且開始想要多了解人類
You want me to know more? You're attention hungry?
師父是想要我多了解一點嗎？ 想我多理會您？
That's not it.
才不是
I'm telling you to come here when that time comes.
我的意思是 當那天來臨時，妳就回來這裡吧
I'll help you out
我這個大魔法使
as the Great Mage
弗蘭梅
Flamme.
親自助妳一臂之力
That's Great Flamme Mage's Notes?
那就是大魔法使弗蘭梅的手記？
Are they real?
是真品嗎？
They're real.
是真品
How do you know?
您怎麼知道？
Frieren was Flamme's top apprentice.
芙莉蓮是弗蘭梅頭號大弟子
The Great Mage Flamme
大魔法使弗蘭梅
is an ancient hero in history books.
可是魔法史書上出現的太古大英雄
Is she seriously from primitive times?
她真的是從原始時代活過來的嗎？
Are there records of her communicating with the dead?
有關於她跟死者對話的紀錄嗎？
It was kindly opened to that page already.
剛好就是打開的這一頁
She knew 1,000 years ago
千年之前，她就已經知道
I would come here?
我會回來這裡了嗎？
As always, she's so obnoxious.
真是一如既往地令人討厭
"In the northernmost point of the continent…"
在大陸極北之境
…I reached Aureole,
我抵達了靈魂安息的所在
the land where souls rest,
靈魂長眠之地
a place which the people
這個世界的人
of this world call heaven.
稱那裡為天國
There were many souls gathered there
在那裡聚集了眾多靈魂
and I talked to my former comrades.
我與昔日戰友進行了對話
This great discovery
這項世紀性的大發現
will advance the study…
一定會讓靈魂方面的研究…
"…of souls in leaps and bounds."
…取得飛躍性的進展
Is this true?
這是真的嗎？
Who knows? She was pretty irresponsible.
誰知道呢？畢竟她本來就很隨興
Heaven does exist.
天國真的存在
It's more convenient that way, isn't it?
因為存在的話就方便多了
That's right.
說得也是
I guess I should believe once in a while.
我想偶爾相信一下也不錯
I wonder where it is, specifically.
真好奇具體位置在哪裡
One second…
我看一下喔…
North of the continent, Ende.
大陸北部，恩德
-Ende? -Yeah…
-恩德的話… -對
It's where the Demon King's castle is now.
就是現今魔王城的所在位置
Why there?
怎麼會是那裡？
Frieren,
芙莉蓮
find Aureole and talk to Himmel.
去找靈魂長眠之地 然後跟欣梅爾好好聊一聊吧
You said you'd help me, right?
妳不是說過要幫我的忙嗎？
You've become crafty, Eisen.
你變狡猾了呢，艾冉
Thanks to Heiter.
全是托海塔的福
Fine. It's not like my journey had a goal or anything.
我明白了 反正我也是漫無目的的旅行
But it's extremely cold
但是魔王城堡那附近
around the Demon King's castle.
超級冷的啊
I don't want to go…
好不想去…
She's already losing enthusiasm.
還沒出發就想打退堂鼓了
-She fell asleep. -What a carefree person.
-她睡著了 -真是無憂無慮
So cold… I don't want to go…
好冷…好不想去…
She's having nightmares.
在作惡夢呢
Is it that cold around the Demon King's castle?
魔王城附近真的那麼冷嗎？
Ende, where the Demon King's castle is,
魔王城所在的恩德
is the northernmost part of the continent.
是這片大陸最北邊的地方
Plus, a lot went down over there.
而且當年在那裡發生過很多事
A lot?
很多事？
This is a bit awkward.
總覺得有點尷尬
Maybe it's time to wake her up?
差不多該叫她起床了？
Mistress Frieren!
芙莉蓮大人…
That didn't work.
叫不醒呢
Hey, Fern.
話說，費倫
Is she a good master?
她是個好師父嗎？
I wonder…
該怎麼說呢…
I don't really know.
我也不知道呢
She is just traveling in pursuit of magic
她只是一邊尋找魔法一邊旅行
and I'm always dragged around.
而我總是被她牽著鼻子到處走
However,
不過
she does seem interested in learning about
她看起來似乎是很想了解
Master Himmel and the others.
欣梅爾大人跟其他人
Maybe
說不定
she just doesn't have much interest in me.
她對我其實沒什麼興趣
Mistress Frieren only made me her apprentice
芙莉蓮大人當初會收我為徒
because of a promise she made with Master Heiter.
也只是因為她跟海塔大人之間的約定
I see.
這樣嗎？
It's just that, she's a very strange person.
但芙莉蓮大人是個很不可思議的人
Once we started traveling,
自從開始一起旅行之後
she would give me birthday presents.
她就會買生日禮物給我
Even though she always seems uninterested in me.
儘管她平常看起來對我漠不關心
I wonder what she's thinking.
真好奇芙莉蓮大人是怎麼想的
She's so strange.
真是奇怪的人
Frieren, you're not staying in the royal capital?
芙莉蓮，妳不打算留在王都嗎？
I'll continue traveling.
我會繼續旅行
On your own?
自己一個人？
It's easier that way.
這樣更輕鬆啊
You're not going to take an apprentice?
妳不打算收個徒弟嗎？
It's better to have someone to talk to when traveling.
旅途中有個人能聊聊天會更好
It's a waste of time.
那只會浪費時間
Even if I teach them things, they die right away.
就算教他們東西，他們也很快就死了
Frieren, that's not what interacting with people is about.
芙莉蓮 人跟人之間的互動不是那樣子的
It is.
是那樣沒錯
My adventures with all of you
跟你們一同冒險的時光
don't even make up one-hundredth of my life.
都還佔不到我人生中的百分之一
You understand me, right?
你的話，應該可以理解我吧？
I…
我…
All right! No more gloomy topics!
好了，不要說這麼沉重的話題！
Today is a joyous day, after all!
畢竟今天是個值得慶祝的日子！
Let's drink!
要開懷暢飲啊！
You just want a reason to drink.
你只是想有個理由喝酒罷了
You got me.
被發現啦
You're always drinking anyway.
反正你一直都在喝吧
Corrupt Priest.
你這個酒肉僧侶
Fern,
費倫
Frieren is a good master.
芙莉蓮是個好師父呢
I guess so.
是啊
Eisen, you really won't come with us?
艾冉，你真的不跟我們來嗎？
Yeah. I told you before, didn't I?
對，我之前也說過吧？
I'll only be a burden.
我現在只會變成你們的累贅
Okay.
好吧
You remember how to get
妳還記得要怎麼
to Ende, right?
去到恩德，對吧？
Yeah. First go to the Wille region,
記得，首先要到威雷地區
then pass through Riegel Canyon
然後穿過里格爾峽谷
and the checkpoint to the northern lands.
然後就是北方諸國的關口了
Sorry, it will be a long journey.
不好意思了，這趟旅途會很漫長
It took us ten years.
我們一行人花了整整十年
I see…
這樣啊
It's the same journey all of you took
接下來要走的是和欣梅爾大人你們
to the Demon King's castle.
前往魔王城時相同的道路啊
That's right.
沒錯
It was a mere ten-year adventure.
只是十年的冒險而已
Can I be a strong warrior?
我可以成為強大的戰士嗎？
-I will become a ghost. -Mistress Frieren.
-我會變成鬼 -芙莉蓮大人
-Travelers… -You're always collecting weird spells.
-旅人啊… -您總是收集奇怪的魔法呢
-Why won't you kill the dragon? -May I have a moment?
-你為什麼不把龍殲滅呢？ -能借一步說話嗎？
-You're looking for it, right? -How stupid.
-你在找它，對吧？ -真是無聊的理由
"Phantoms of the dead."
這就是死者的幻影？
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻